[SPEAKER_00]: And, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a Sanyuta Nikaya 5521 to Mahānāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've heard that on one occasion the Blessed One was staying among the Sakyans near Kapilavatthu in Nīgrodha's park.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then Mahanāma the Sakyan went to the Blessed One, and on arrival, having bowed down to Him, said to one side.
[SPEAKER_00]: As he was sitting there, he said, Sometimes when I enter Kapilavatthu in the evening, after visiting the Blessed One or with the monks who inspire the mind, I meet up with a runaway elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: A runaway horse, a runaway chariot, a runaway cart, or a runaway person.
[SPEAKER_00]: At times like that, my mindfulness, with regard to the Blessed One, gets muddled.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mindfulness with regard to the dhamma and the saṅgha gets muddled.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thought occurs to me, if I were to die at this moment, what would be my destination?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would be my future course?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then,
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha replies, have no fear, Mahānāma, have no fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your death will not be a bad one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your demise will not be bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one's mind has long been nurtured with conviction, with virtue, with learning, with relinquishment, with discernment, then when the body, endowed with the form, composed of the four primary elements, born from mother and father, nourished with rice and porridge, subject to inconstancy, rubbing, pressing, dissolution and dispersion,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is eaten by crows, vultures, hawks, dogs, hyenas, or all sorts of creatures, nevertheless the mind, long nurtured with conviction, nurtured with virtue, learning relinquishment and discernment, rises upward and separates out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose a man were to throw a jar or ghee or a jar of oil into a deep lake of water where it would break.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the Buddha repeats, have no fear, Mahānāma, your death will not be a bad one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, in Saṃgītā 5522, the next one, it's the same story, and same concern from Mahānāma, and then the Buddha tells him that same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have no fear, Mahānāma, have no fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your death will not be a bad one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your demise will not be bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: A disciple of the noble ones, when endowed with four qualities, leans towards Nibbāna, slants towards Nibbāna, inclines towards Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which four?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a case when the disciple of the Noble Ones is endowed with verified confidence in the Awakened One.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indeed, the Blessed One is worthy and rightly self-awakened, consummate in knowledge and conduct, well-gone and expert with regard to the world, unexcelled as a trainer for those people fit to be tamed, teacher of divine and human beings, awakened and blessed.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's endowed with verified confidence in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dhamma is well expounded.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the Blessed One, it's to be seen here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's timeless, inviting verification, pertinent to be realized by the wise for themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's endowed with a verified confidence in the saṅgha, the saṅgha of the Blessed One's disciples.
[SPEAKER_00]: They practice well, practice straightforwardly, practice methodically, and practice masterfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the four types of noble disciples, taken as pairs, eight when taken as individual types.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll address all these things afterwards, because the sutta is quite short, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: They are the saṅgha of the blessed one's disciple, worthy of gifts, worthy of hospitality, worthy of offerings, worthy of respect, an incomparable field of merit for the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that noble disciple is also endowed with virtues that are appealing to the noble ones, untorn, unbroken, unspotted, unsplattered, liberating, praised by the wise, untarnished, leading to concentration or composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose a tree was leaning towards the east, slanting towards the east, inclining towards the east.
[SPEAKER_00]: When its root is cut, which way would it fall?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it would fall whichever way it was leaning, slanting and inclining, Lord, said Mahānāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, Mahānāma, disciple of the Noble Ones, when endowed with four qualities, leans towards Nibbāna, slants towards Nibbāna and inclines towards Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of concludes the reading of the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as it can be seen from these two suttas, which is probably like one instance, but the Buddha gave numerous examples to Mahānāma and then he was remembered or compilers would have divided it into subsequent suttas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as it can be seen from the suttas, Mahānāma was a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he was at least a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means he has understood the dhamma and the Four Noble Truths and what the practice for complete cessation of suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's important to kind of recognize because
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes a bit more than just being a good Buddhist, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, every Buddhist today would say, yeah, of course, I have confidence in the Buddha, that he was the greatest, and I absolutely venerate the saṅgha, they're the greatest disciples, and the dhamma is perfectly expounded.
[SPEAKER_00]: But these stock phrases from the suttas, they don't mean just a mere belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're basically like a condensed way
[SPEAKER_00]: of just saying that his understanding of the dhamma would have verified his confidence in the Buddha and any subsequent disciple of the Buddha they would be teaching the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, he was a sotāpanna with an internal criteria to tell for himself what the right dhamma is and what isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, you know, as we said so many times before, in the course of history, in the course of passing down these suttas and being memorized and then compiled,
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much all the nuances are gone, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the individual variations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, whenever somebody's a sotāpanna, whenever somebody, in whatever idiosyncratic way, might describe their understanding of the principle of the dhamma, well, all we get is a stock passage that says he has a verified confidence in the Buddha, the dhamma, and the saṅgha, and he's clear about those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bit more than that, than just being convinced that those three things are the best three holy trinity in the world, to be saved, or to be safe from the perilous rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only one that could be... that can say it's truly safe, would be somebody who's at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nothing shorter than sotāpatti guarantees safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's mentioned in other suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's like a... it's an imperative for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And speaking now of sotāpatti, actually, I mean, the sutta doesn't kind of touch upon that directly, but it does sort of raise a question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Mahānāma, as a sotāpanna,
[SPEAKER_00]: Didn't know what his... how... whether his rebirth will be good or bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody today, after reading all the suttas, might wonder about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, how is that possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like Sotāpanna has said so many times that they cannot go to bad destination and they have seven... seven beings at most.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seven bhavas before they will make an end to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, actually, in other suttas, we get to see how the whole idea of the four stages of enlightenment came to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, there were no sotāpānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was no talk about sotāpānas, or sakadāgāmīs, or anāgāmīs.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was those who practice the dhamma and those who don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those who practice the dhamma would have been the ones who've seen the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was like, exactly for those reasons, when one of those disciples died, Ananda would go to the Buddha and ask, oh, such-and-such passed away, he was practicing the dhamma, he was following your instruction, what was his destination?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha would reply,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he was... he was saved.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was basically a non-returner.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would... he would have been... he would have been reborn in some higher heaven and he would make an end to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then somebody else died.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, he would return one more time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that has been happening for quite a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: And at one point, when Ananda went to the Buddha again with such a question, the Buddha said, well, if...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever some disciple of the Tathāgata dies, you come and ask me about their destination, it's going to be a bit of a hassle for me, and it's becoming a bit of a hassle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then the Buddha formulated these external criteria, so that anybody who understands the dhamma can then use that to infer where
[SPEAKER_00]: Other people, eh... people who were passed away, eh... are, in terms of their understanding of the dhamma, like, eh... in terms of their practice, sorry, and also, eh... they can use it to apply to themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... as I said before, there was no, eh... sotāpatti or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was just like... either you're practicing the dhamma successfully, or getting closer to it, or you're not, or you're going in a completely opposite direction, or you're not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the Buddha outlined these four stages,
[SPEAKER_00]: They're kind of like a... like a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't say cornerstones, they're more like a kind of stations on the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, quite arbitrarily decided upon certain, say, relevant aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sotapaṭṭhā is relevant, because, obviously, it's the arising of the dhammāyā, how the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the understanding
[SPEAKER_00]: of what the path is, what suffering is, what the cessation of suffering is, and how to fully develop that cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of important.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's like, okay, well, that's certainly one first station, as in, like, something that cannot be missed, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the second one, sakadāgāmī, see, that's already was quite subjectively described as, oh, he weakened.
[SPEAKER_00]: the other two fetters, the fetter of lust and aversion, and in a number of other suttas, it's completely omitted.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha would talk about sotāpanna and then go and talk about anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: So sakadāgāmī doesn't even occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, weakened.
[SPEAKER_00]: At what level?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's more like
[SPEAKER_00]: A reference, kind of a guideline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, obviously, the third anāgāmī would be... okay, that's also significant, in a sense of... it has, like a... say, a perceivable change.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just weakening of certain fetters, but it's abandonment of sensuality and ill-will, which are obviously two major, kind of, forces in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it would be unmistaken, equally unmistaken, as the rising of the dhammāy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, arahantship would be cessation of all the fetters and freedom from, obviously, all of the asavas.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, even that, there's so many suttas where anāgāmīs would have overestimated themselves and thought they were arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha would say, oh, yeah, half of these monks, they declared arahantship, they declared it rightly, but the other half, they overestimated themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like that they were wrong-wrong, in a sense, but it's just
[SPEAKER_00]: The asavas, the remnants of the fetters that were left, were so subtle that nothing was coming up.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were practically free.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why even the Buddha himself often, when we talk about somebody successfully practicing the dhamma to completion, he would say they would reach arahantship here and now,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if there is some unspecified residue left, even he couldn't... could not necessarily tell always, there would be reborn in pure abodes as a non-returner, never return from that, and then they would make an end of suffering over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's important, like, so even when it comes to the first three fetters that Sotāpanna is free from,
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to realize it's the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, achieving sotāpāt is the same practice that you do for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, I can practice for sotāpāna and aim at these three fetters and not do the rest of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practice of dhamma is the practice of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not fulfilling it completely, you'll be at least a sotāpāna or sakadāgāmī or anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fulfilling it completely, you'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh... the reason why I insist on this, and bring it up often, is because, like, it quite clearly says, for example, the right intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, well, it says that one cannot enter upon the right path, sotāpati, while practicing the wrong path, while not maintaining the right path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the right path?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the right path is the right recollection, right intention, well, the noble little path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the point is, when it comes to right intention, it's the intention of non-lust, non-cruelty, non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the right intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why even if somebody says, oh, you know, as a householder, I can't abandon my life, because I have duties and stuff, so I can't practice for Arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on account of that, they might feel excused from not restraining sensuality and other kind of aspects of the path that are deemed later in practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the start, in order to enter the rightful path, as the sutra says, you need to maintain these rightful aspects of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't possibly be engaging in sensuality, ill-will, physically, verbally, while somehow, miraculously, having a mind of no intention towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And other suttas do say that, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: That one can engage with sensuality without those perceptions already being established and perverted internally on the level of that intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, like, Mahanāma
[SPEAKER_00]: Or any Sotāpanna doesn't need to know about rebirths.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that whole thing of seven bhāvas, that came from the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: He formulated that, and because people had faith in him, they, okay, took it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a measure of Sotāpatti, whether you see your next rebirth or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, it's not a measure of arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sariputta couldn't see anything, in his own words, let alone other rebirths, and what's waiting for whom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is the measure of sotāpati?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that first major, as I said, station, that major kind of point, which is the recognition of where dukkha comes from, what dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like completely unmistaken understanding of what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then, obviously, implicates the counterpart as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you clearly understand what suffering is, you clearly understand what that cessation of suffering is as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the whole Noble Eightfold Path becomes just like an absolute thorough fulfillment of that cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is what a sotāpanna understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what Mahānāma understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, like, in this sutta, where he... when he says his mindfulness was muddled and so on, it doesn't mean that he became a pūtujana when he got scared.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means that that broader context of clarity was somewhat obstructed because he obviously hasn't fully trained his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when certain extreme situations come up, they would have clouded, as I said, the broadness of the context that he would have otherwise been maintaining.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not to say that he would have been fully overwhelmed, gripped and forgot where the actual dukkha comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's inconceivable to forget, because, obviously, it's not just on a level of information.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like I learned yesterday, dukkha comes from there and tomorrow somebody might prove that wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's literally seeing the state of mind, citta, like cittanimitta, that animal we talk about, seeing suffering like completely, inescapably connected with that very craving of that animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when animal is exhibiting craving, suffering is felt regardless of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: When animal is not exhibiting the craving, there is no suffering felt whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see both, clear as a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly now...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so, how do I make the animal not crave?
[SPEAKER_00]: Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a magical, mystical, meditation experience, that suddenly sorted everything out.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a recognition, through obviously already having certain recognitions of where that animal is, where your state of mind is, what your citta is,
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's then recognition of, okay, so it needs to be an absolute, thorough, complete training of this entity, of this citta, so that it becomes incapable of craving, even traces of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I will become incapable of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: As straightforward as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not to say it's easy, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Mahānāma could not have doubted that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, sotāpād is not measured by knowledge of your rebirths.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahantship is not measured by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just an external criteria that can be used skillfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in this case, you know, he was... he wasn't, like, necessarily, as I said, overwhelmed by suffering a grip, but he admits, oh, his perspective diminished and he thought, if I were to die now, would that matter?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where would I go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where would I be reborn?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a kind of reassurance, coming from the Buddha himself, that, well, don't worry about it, because really what matters is what you've been doing up to that point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you been training your citta correctly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you becoming a consummate established in virtue?
[SPEAKER_00]: How the sutra says, in discernment, in composure, in being able to endure things on the right level?
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you been doing that most of the time?
[SPEAKER_00]: If yes, you don't have to worry about the last moment of your death and so on, even, even if the perspective diminishes there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's... well, as the similes explain, it's like if the tree has been growing in one direction, doesn't matter how you cut it, from what angle you come, it's gonna fall in that direction, because it's already heavily slanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: To incline the mind towards nibbāna, the more you do so, the better it will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, it doesn't matter from what angle the death comes, and whether you're prepared for it or not, whether you're anticipating it or not, it will go that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why the four stages of enlightenment are kind of just like an external guideline.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you can use to review your mind, to review your state, but fundamentally, the practice in and of itself, it's the practice towards that Noble Eightfold Path, towards the purification through virtue, sense restraint and taming of that animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, as we've described in other talks on the basis of other suttas, that's the practice for puthujjana as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Vitujana needs to do, pretty much, try and emulate, as perfectly as possible, the practice of dhamma, which is the practice of the Noble Eightfold Path, which can then enable them to actually get the sense of what the citta is, what that entity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, everything else, obviously, that depends on that, can begin to grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, I think we address this, like, if such knowledge of rebirths is not available, how can one know for sure, without doubt, that there are ten sotāpatti or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: I just answered that, didn't I?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, so, obviously, I also addressed the very common view that... and that's obviously very common in the... certainly in the buddhist cultures, that it's the... what you think... what your last thought is at the moment of death, that's what determines your rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, obviously, these both suttas show that as completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because not just that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you think about it, it's like, so what?
[SPEAKER_00]: You could practice the whole life, but then have one weird thought at the end of the life, like Mahānāma perspective maybe shrunk a bit, and that will completely send you the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't make sense in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it also, you realize, the reason why people would kind of almost prefer that type of view is because it's, you know, it allows for a great deal of wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you're gonna have the right thought because you're such a faithful Buddhist.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, eh... completely to not feel responsible for everything you're doing in the meantime while you're alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: For not slanting that tree while you still can.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I'll just have a magical...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right thought of right faith and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unshakable faith when I'm dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the chances of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you do, by the way, even if you cut the tree...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, imagine how the tree is slanting away from nibbāna, not towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your last thought is the absolutely perfect thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mind you, your whole life preceding that was absolutely unrestrained, opposite of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if your last thought was perfect, that could be, say, the absolutely perfect angle, perfect wedge cut on a tree, perfect notch, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you think that tree still wouldn't fall in the direction that's heavily slanted?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it would.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your perfect thought would not make a difference if your life was not being led according to the principles that the Buddha described, principles of training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: It kind of clearly shows that it's just on the level of wishful thinking and almost kind of mystified ideas of rebirth, that conveniently, as I said, would be taking away or feeling you're not so responsible for stuff you do on a day-to-day basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I actually got a question regarding the second sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, one of the things that's often recommended for householders are the six anusatis, like recollection of Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha, virtue, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was wondering, similarly to that you said, that you can imitate or try to emulate the Noble Eightfold Path,
[SPEAKER_00]: How should the pūtūjana emulate the first three recollections, like Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha, which then... Well, again, it's not the recollection of the actual images or statues or whatever you think the Buddha looked like.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a recollection of the values.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you think the Buddha, do you think sexual intercourse?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think the Buddha, do you think punching somebody in the face?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think saṅgha, you see a group of people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you think backstabbing, gossip, lying, stealing, malversations?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means to recollect the Buddha, dhamma and saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not light cheap incense about 108 times to a shrine and think about fantasy and your imaginary friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, recollect the values.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think the Buddha, what does that stand for?
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, contrast your behavior to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contrast your planning, future behavior to that, things that you're planning to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, yeah, it's an actual recollection of the right, suitable, useful, wholesome contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That obviously go hand in hand with virtue and that sensory strength and right composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it means to recollect these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, actually, the Buddha did say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: For a noble disciple, householder, noble disciple, who frequently recollects the Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha and the unbroken virtue, they have the pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, same description like for jhāna, the pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where composure comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where peace and the recognition of the existing happiness comes from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a way, any recollection that one does, should always be concerning one's actions, one's current way of being?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any recollection that one does, should be inherently based on the values that one is contrasting to the current actions, previous actions, the ones you're planning to do, the current, the current... Not, not like... Or think about, as I said, think about the eighth factor of paticca-samupāda or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that carries no value.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might.
[SPEAKER_00]: For somebody who would have thought about it long enough and practiced rightly, it might carry the value of simultaneity and sense restraint and dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for more people, certainly in the beginning, it won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just going to be an abstract theory that you're going to convince yourself you're thinking about dhamma, while you're actually not.
[SPEAKER_00]: While your experience is still having unchecked passion, unchecked ill-will, unchecked hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it always needs to come down onto the level of actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you think about the Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha, as I said, those stock phrases, you think about the values that are now being compared to your currently maintained values to things you're doing, things you're planning to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pleasant abiding here now would be a product of realizing I'm actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm in line with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it would be the result of realizing that you're aligned with that, or if you were not, of aligning yourself with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are recollecting these values, contrasted against your actions, recent actions, the ones you're planning to do, the choice becomes very clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your choice becomes clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I follow what I clearly know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is aligned with the Buddha, the dhamma, the saṅgha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I don't follow that?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no external excuses or reason necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, but I'm a householder... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that comes second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right there and then, you have a clear choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a value of the Noble Eightfold Path, as I said, and the value opposite of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't do both.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I have a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I give this up, I'm choosing the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And tomorrow I might have to do the same, and the day after I have to do the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But right there and then, the choice that arises is very clear and it's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, okay, so what's stopping me from choosing the right practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's stopping me from choosing the Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, me not choosing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's stopping me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every single time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else can come in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: No wife, no kids, nothing can come in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: No duties, no business, no family.
[SPEAKER_01]: No other monasteries, other monks, nothing can come between.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's yours and yours only.